A Guide to the Helena Lefroy Caperton Papers 1918-1961
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Helena Lefroy Caperton Papers 1918-1961
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 3
6 linear feet
Helena Lefroy Caperton
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift to the Special Collections and Archives Department from Mrs. Barry Bingham and Mrs. Donald Stevens in 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
Helena Trench Lefroy was born on 18 August 1878 in her grandfather's (John Henry Montague) house at 118 East Franklin Street (Linden Row), Richmond, Virginia. Her parents were Sallie Watson Montague and Jeffrey Arthur Lefroy. As a child, Helena spent many summers with her father's parents at Aghaderg, County Down, North Ireland. Her recollections of these years can be found in "Some Reminiscences of an Ulster Childhood". She and her mother resided with the Montagues in Linden Row after the death of her father in 1883.
Helena married Clifford Randolph Caperton on "Wyndridge", Monroe County, West Virginia 16 November 1897. They had seven children. After 1920, Mrs. Caperton began to write seriously and had many articles and short stories published. "The Honest Wine Merchant" won the O. Henry Award in 1930 and the O'Brien Anthology of the Best Short Stories gave a star rating to "Lost Governess". She wrote regular book reviews for the Richmond Times-Dispatch and the Courier- Journal (Louisville, KY).
Helena Lefroy Caperton died after a short illness on 27 September 1962.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, manuscripts of short stories, articles, reviews, and other literary efforts, reviews of Caperton's works, bills and receipts, photographs and other papers relating to her career and family life (1918-1961). Includes correspondence with publishers and periodicals and material on Virginia and Irish legends and folktales, and social life in Virginia and England. Correspondents include William Rose Benet, Edward O'Brien, Dorothy Parker, Charles Scribner, Claude Swanson and Alexander Waddell.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically then chronologically.
Organization
Series I--Unpublished Fiction and Articles (n.d., 1924, 1928, 1931, 1934, 1939, 1947-1948, 1951)
Series II-- Receipted Bills and Canceled Checks (1924-1961, majority in the 1950s)
Series III-- Letters from Magazines and Publishers (n.d., 1920, 1923-26, 1929-1941, 1943, 1946-1947, 1949-1952, 1955, 1970)
Series IV--Family Letters, Fan Letters, Published Newspaper Articles and Reviews, Photographs (n.d., 1918, 1923, 1931, 1934, 1937-1939, 1943, 1949-1952, 1954-1955)
Series V--Irish Fairy Stories, Irish Childhood, The Richmond German, Sketches of Old Richmond, Assorted Short Stories and Articles (n.d., 1932, 1939, 1947, 1950-1953, 1958, 1960, 1970)
Series VI-- Printed Articles and Short Stories in Magazines and Newspapers (1902, 1921, 1924, 1929-1934, 1937-1939)
Series VII-- Artifacts (3 pieces)
Contents List
- Series I-Unpublished fiction and Articles
  - Deep Waters (Box 1)
  - Dove of Peace (Box 1)
  - A Friendly Guide to Richmond (Box 1)
  - Foggies (Box 1)
  - Frost Tonight (Box 1)
  - Gods Fool (Box 1)
  - The Haunted House in Linden Row (Box 1)
  - I Elizabeth, Take Thee Philip (Box 1)
  - Liebestrom (Box 1)
  - The Little Blind God and Mr. Volstead (Box 1)
  - Locked Out in London (Box 1)
  - Monsieur (Box 1)
  - The Nigger in the Woodpile. Today's Aesop's Fables (Box 1)
  - The Old House (Box 1)
  - One Pound Seventeen Shillings and Sixpence (Box 1)
  - The Peggy Cranford Books-Peggy at Roundabout Castle (Box 1)
  - Return of the Soldier (Box 1)
  - A Royal Visit 1920 (Box 1)
  - Reunion (Box 1)
  - The Reproof Valliant (Box 1)
  - Saturday Evening Post (Box 1)
  - Strange Acquaintance (Box 1)
  - The Falls thy Shadow (Box 1)
  - This Reward of Parenthood (Box 1)
  - Verses Sent with Christmas Gifts 1925 (Box 1)
  - When the Wild West Came to Richmond (Box 1)
  - When the Lights Go On (Box 1)
  - The Winner (Box 1)
  - Wisdom is Justified of Her Children (Box 1)
  - With Angels and Arch-Angels (Box 1)
  - With Trailing Clouds of Glory (Box 1)
  - Foreword (Box 1)
  - Adventure in Explosives (Box 1)
  - Apron Strings...American Style (Box 1)
  - Buried Treasure (Box 1)
  - The Chalfonte Hotel (Box 1)
  - Just a Moment Mr. Conquest (Box 1)
  - Cordially Yours New York (Box 1)
  - To the Blue Gown (Box 2)
  - Miss Angel Gabriel (Box 2)
  - Like a Falcon Flying (Box 2)
  - Our Debutantes of Today and Yesterday (Box 2)
  - The Prince and the Pauper by Mark Twain (Box 2)
  - Virginia is a State of Mind (Box 2)
  - The Voice of the People (Box 2)
  - Sketch of a Lady Wallis Simpson (Box 2)
  - Tour of Historic Homes and Gardens in the Tidewater of Virginia for Restoration of Wakefield, April 29th to May 3rd (Box 2)
  - In Loco Parentis (Box 2)
  - New Grandmothers for Old (Box 2)
  - The Dolls House of Mayfair (Box 2)
  - The Doctors Story (Box 2)
  - Father of the Bride (Box 2)
  - Frankincense (Box 2)
  - The Home of Mr. Jacqueline Taylor at Richmond, Virginia (Box 2)
  - The Wedding (Box 2)
  - The Ballad of Webspinner (Box 2)
  - Welcome (Box 2)
  - Philanthropist (Box 2)
  - A Club Memoir 1930 (Box 2)
  - The Christmas Star (Box 2)
  - The Romantic New Orlianians (Box 2)
  - Gallery of Ghosts (Box 2)
  - The Golden Stallion (Box 2)
  - Lecture Introduction (Box 2)
  - Our Latin Quarter (Box 2)
  - Our Plum Street (Box 2)
  - The Magnificent Deception (Box 2)
  - The Mid-Wife's Story (Box 2)
  - Oblivion (Box 2)
  - Negrofoot (Box 2)
  - The Old House (Box 2)
  - Pirate Sapphires (Box 2)
  - The Primrose Path of Dear Papa (Box 2)
  - Seaport in Virginia (Box 2)
  - The Seventh Window (Box 2)
  - How We Raised Our Six Daughters (Box 2)
  - Vagabond Parents (Box 2)
  - Who Giveth This Woman? (Box 2)
  - Time Gambols Withal (Box 2)
- Series II-Receipt Bills and Canceled Checks
  - Annual Dues Association (Box 3)
  - Bank Transactions-English Funds (Box 3)
  - Bank Transactions-Local (Box 3)
  - Clothing (Box 3)
  - Funeral Home-Memorial Marker (Box 3)
  - Gifts (Box 3)
  - Groceries (Box 3)
  - Home Furnishings and Repair (Box 3)
  - Home Improvements and Repairs (Box 3)
  - Hospital and Veterinary Hospital (Box 3)
  - Insurance (Box 3)
  - Nursery (Box 3)
  - Pharmacy (Box 3)
  - Printing (Box 3)
  - Public Utilities (Box 3)
  - Royalty Statements (Box 3)
  - Taxes (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Series III-Letters from Magazines and Publishers
  - Ausburg Publishing House March 22, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House June 8, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House November 8, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House December 19, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House January 9, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House March 27, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House May 16, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House May 26, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Ausburg Publishing House March 6, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Brandt and Brandt October 5, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Brandt and Brandt October 14, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Brandt and Brandt October 20, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Brandt and Brandt June 8, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Stringfellow Barr October 3, 1932 (Box 4)
  - The Binghams August 30, 1955 (Box 4)
  - The Binghams October 13, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Struther Maxwell Burt May 11, 1938
  - Alan Campbell September 17 (Box 4)
  - Cecil and Presbrely, Inc. February 15, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Cecil and Presbrely, Inc. February 26, 1946 (Box 4)
  - B.J. Chute November 13, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Cranz, Oscar September 14, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company January 14, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company February 18, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company February 25, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company March 21, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Philip Cudall October 4, ? (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. November 25, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. December 30, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. June 5, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. July 3, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. July 29, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. August 25, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. July 5, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Curtis Brown Ltd. November 13, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Exposition Press June 17, 1952 (Box 4)
  - The Forum Quarterly May 2, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Douglas S. Freeman August 9, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Douglas S. Freeman September 11, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Bess Furman December 5, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Garrett and Massie, Inc. July 19, 1943 (Box 4)
  - The Greenbrier and Cottages November 21, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Benn Hall Associates (Box 4)
  - Fanny Hathworth (Box 4)
  - Holiday December 13, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Holiday April 19, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Holiday May 19, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Holiday March 5, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Holiday July 2, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Holiday August 15, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Holland's October 28, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Holland's March 7, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Holland's April 3, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Holland's May 8, 1940 (Box 4)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company March 18, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Household Magazines September 4, 1931 (Box 4)
  - Mrs. C. Huffman October 19, 1949 (Box 4)
  - B.S. Hume September 30, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson July 10, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson July 18, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson August 25, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson September 7, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson October 24, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson November 6, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson December 4, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson February 5, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson February 16, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson April 12, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson June 6, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Margot Johnson September 6, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Alfred A. Knopf March 27, 1940 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal January 9, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal January 14, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal January 19, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal March 5, 1920 (Box 4)
  - April 1, 1920 April 1, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal April 21, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal May 5, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal May 7, 1920 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal July 6, 1933 (Box 4)
  - The Ladies Home Journal January 18, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Life October 29, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Life November 12, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Life November 19, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Life September 27, 1955 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. March 5, 1931 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. July 2, 1931 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. July 3, 1931 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. September 24, 1931 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 5, 1932 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 10, 1932 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. March 1, 1932 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 13, 1932 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. March 2, 1932 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. June 7, 1933 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. June 14, 1933 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. July 7, 1933 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 13, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 24, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. February 26, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. March 14, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. April 6, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. April 24, 1934 (Box 4)
  - McIntosh and Otis, Inc. August (Box 4)
  - William Maner March 8, 1951 (Box 4)
  - William Morrow and Company, Inc. November 30, 1940 (Box 4)
  - National League of American Pen Women (Box 4)
  - Edward J. O'Brien February 27, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Edward J. O'Brien January 20, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Dorothy Parker (Box 4)
  - The People's Home Journal October 19, 1923 (Box 4)
  - The People's Home Journal November 16, 1923 (Box 4)
  - The People's Home Journal December 1, 1923 (Box 4)
  - The People's Home Journal April 22, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The People's Home Journal June 26, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Mary Pritchett September 26, 1941 (Box 4)
  - G.P. Putnam's Sons May 8, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Richmond Chamber of Commerce November 12, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Dr. M. Pierce Rucker March 2, 1932 (Box 4)
  - St. Catherine's School April 12, 1933 (Box 4)
  - St. John's Church October 7, ? (Box 4)
  - Charles Scribners Sons August 25, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Sons of the American Revolution March 29, 1947 (Box 4)
  - The Southern Planter March 11, 1931 (Box 4)
  - The Spur March 6, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The Spur March 24, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The Spur June 12, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The Spur July 1, 1924 (Box 4)
  - The Spur October 14, 1925 (Box 4)
  - E. Strudwick, Jr. February 24, 1941 (Box 4)
  - The Times-Picayune February 22, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Tupper and Love, Inc. July 15, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Tupper and Love, Inc. July 31, 1952 (Box 4)
  - The Valentine Museum November 12, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Frank W. Vincent Agency September 4, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Cecelia Washington October 25, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Woman's Home Companion June 10, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Woman's Home Companion March 5, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert F. Wright March 7, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert F. Wright August 28, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert F. Wright April 24, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert F. Wright October 20, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Gilbert F. Wright September 10, 1943 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Seriev IV-Family Letters, Fan Letters, Published Newspaper Articles and Reviews, Photographs
  - Viscountess Astor July 5, 1923 (Box 5)
  - The Baltimore Sun March 23, 1943 (Box 5)
  - London February 1, 1938 (Box 5)
  - William Rose Benet February 25, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Lucinda Trabree Brent (Box 5)
  - Lt. Richard C. Brown February 26, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Lt. Alan Campbell March 4, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Margaret Dashiell March 3, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Walter H. Gray March 5, 1943 (Box 5)
  - George Wilmer Hodgson February 24, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Hully March 2, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Annette Lefroy October 27, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Edward H. Lefroy January 26, 1937 (Box 5)
  - George Lefroy February 19, 1918 (Box 5)
  - Minna Lefroy April 25; May 2; June 1, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Mrs. John David Leitch February 13, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Mrs. Mary Loftie May 27, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Mildred March 12, ? (Box 5)
  - Newark Evening News February 11, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Virginia Reynolds March 3, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Sal March 6, 1943 (Box 5)
  - The Southern Literary Messenger March 13, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Claude Swanson April 24, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Alexander Wilbourne Waddell February 24, 1943 (Box 5)
  - Florence Weiss August 11, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Reviews (Box 5)
  - Articles and Letter to the paper by Caperton (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: The Loved and Envied (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: The Loved and Envied (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: The Feast of July (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: A World of Love (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Money to Burn (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Beyond the PawPaw Trees (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Tales My Grandmother Told Me (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: A House and Its Head (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Elizabeth the Queen (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: A King's Story (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Royal Mother, the Story of Queen Mother Elizabeth and Her Family (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Life in a Nutshell (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: White House Profile (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: A Degree of Prudery (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Light as the Morning (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: The View from the Parsonage (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Steamboat Gothic (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Shadows in Silver (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Houses Virginians Have Loved (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Charles Dickens (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Children of the Rainbow (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: English Life and Leisure (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: What Did It Mean? (Box 5)
  - Book Reviews by Caperton: Don't Look Round (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous: John Rolfe's Letter of 1616 November 3, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous: Thalhimers Honors Richmond Authors (Box 5)
  - Photographs: Christmas Card of Clifford and Helena Caperton (Box 5)
  - Photograph: Christmas Card of a Small Nude Child Sitting by a Pool (Box 5)
- Series V-Irish Fairy Stories; Irish Childhood; The Richmond German; Sketches of Old Richmond; Assorted Short Stories and Articles
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: My Lord Lion (Box 6)
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: The Princess Discontent (Box 6)
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: The Toad's Journal (Box 6)
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: Tom and the Ogre (Box 6)
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: The Ballad of Four Brothers (Box 6)
  - Revised Irish Fairy Stories and Ballades: The Ballad of Webspinner (Box 6)
  - Irish Childhood (Box 6)
  - Record and History of the Richmond German from 1866 to 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Sketches of an Older Richmond (Box 6)
  - Unkept Vineyards (Box 7)
  - Then Falls Thy Shadow (Box 8)
  - Wedding March (Box 9)
- Series VI-Printed Articles and Short Stories in Magazines and Newspapers
  - Captain Mary Green (Box 10)
  - How We Brought Up Our Six Daughters (Box 10)
  - In Loco Parentis (Box 10)
  - I've Been to London to Visit the Queen (Box 10)
  - Mellow Days; a Sketch of Mid-Victorian Richmond (Box 10)
  - Our Debutantes (Box 10)
  - Our Latin Quarter (Box 10)
  - Richmond Debutantes (Box 10)
  - Second Street (Box 10)
  - Time Gambols Withal (Box 10)
  - Autumn Garner (Box 10)
  - Brides' Lottery (Box 10)
  - For Richer For Poorer (Box 10)
  - Great Will be Your Reward (Box 11)
  - The Honest Wine Merchant (Box 11)
  - Just Plain Husband (Box 11)
  - The Magnificent Deception (Box 11)
  - Negro Foot (Box 11)
  - The Old House (Box 11)
  - The Rake (Box 11)
  - The Seventh Window (Box 11)
  - Taxi (Box 11)
  - Routine Flight (Box 11)
- Series VII-Artifacts
  - Museum Pieces (Box 10)
    The silver dagger and a Buddha and the sailor's plaid scarf-all relate to a story called the Chinese Lady from the Bood Legends of a Virginian.